Guide to the Rocky Chin Papers WAG.325
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Rocky Chin Papers
1968-2016
1984-2001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Chin, Rocky, 1947-
Chen, May Ying
WAG.325
14.5 Linear Feet in 20 manuscript boxes, 1 record carton, 1 half manuscript box, 1 flat box, 1 oversize flat box, and 5 oversize folders in shared housing
637 Megabytes in 68 computer files.
1 videodiscs (dvd)
1 videocassettes (vhs)
Rockwell "Rocky" Chin has been active in labor, community, and civil rights struggles in New York City since the early 1980s, particularly through his involvement with various Asian Pacific American (APA) organizations. Spanning between 1966 to 2016, with the bulk of materials from 1984-2001, this collection documents Chin's work as an activist, his involvement in political campaigns, and his teaching. Materials include correspondence, memoranda, meeting minutes, newsletters, publications and reports, legal briefs, brochures, event and conference programs, speech and article drafts, flyers, press releases, and newspaper clippings. A large portion of the collection pertains to Chin's service on the New York City Commission on Human Rights and materials related to Asian American movement groups like Basement Workshop, APA labor unions, the Asian American studies movement, demonstrations and rallies organized around redistricting issues, and Asian American involvement in various local and national political campaigns. There are also collected publications, reports, and audiovisual recordings related to Asian American cultural events and labor and community activism.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Rocky Chin and his wife, May Chen, in January 2012. The accession number associated with this gift is 2012.008.
Rocky Chin donated an additional 4 boxes of collected periodicals and recordings in 2018. The accession number associated with this gift is 2018.025.
Appraisal
After the first donation in 2012, approximately 0.25 linear feet of widely distributed newspapers (NY Times, Washington Post, etc.) from the 2008 presidential election were discarded. During processing in 2020, out-of-scope, duplicate, and mold-damaged materials were deaccessioned, including an election banner, campaign signs, optical discs, and conference proceedings.
Arrangement
The Rocky Chin Papers is arranged into three series:
Series I. Activism
Series II. Political Campaigns
Series III. Teaching
Biographical Note
Rockwell "Rocky" Chin has lived and worked in Lower Manhattan since the early 1980s, where he has been active in labor, community, and civil rights struggles. He was born in Washington, D.C. and completed his undergraduate studies at Lehigh University. Chin went on to receive a master's degree in City Planning from Yale University in 1971 and a law degree from the University of Southern California in 1974.
At the New York City Commission on Human Rights (HRC), Chin served as Assistant Deputy Commissioner for Community Relations, Acting General Counsel, and Supervising Attorney. In addition to prosecuting and mediating discrimination cases at the Commission, Chin participated in the HRC's efforts to eliminate exclusive male-only private clubs, address discrimination against immigrants, and eliminate barriers for people with disabilities.
In September 1992, Chin helped organize the first City Hall conference addressing the concerns of the city's Asian Pacific American communities. He attended the founding convention of the National Rainbow Coalition (now Rainbow/PUSH), helped coordinate support for Jesse Jackson and David Dinkins during their successful New York City campaigns, served as Treasurer for the Honorable Doris Ling-Cohen, and was the campaign manager for Sau Ngar Li and Danny Yip's Community School District 2 campaigns.
Chin is a member of the American Bar Association's Coordinating Committee on Immigration, the New York City Organizing Committee for Citizen Action, the New York Immigration Coalition, the Lower East Side Call for Justice, and the Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance, AFL-CIO. He has served as honorary board member of the Asian American Arts Alliance and as board member of Mobilizing For Justice (MFJ) Legal Services, Inc. For many years, Chin also served as Vice Chair of Leadership Education for Asian Pacifics (LEAP) and as Civil Rights Chair of the National Asian Pacific American Bar Association (NAPABA). He is a founder of the Asian American Bar Association of New York (AABANY) and a former president of AABANY.
In 2001, Chin ran and was defeated in the race for City Council as representative for District 1. He is a former member of Community Board 3 (Lower East Side).
Chin has taught at Hunter College, City College, Cornell University's School of Law, and New York University. He is married to May Chen, who served as an officer for Local 23-25 and as International Vice President of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (later UNITE, UNITE/HERE, and Workers United).
From 2007-2015, Chin served as Director of the Office of Equal Opportunity and Diversity at the New York State Division of Human Rights. He has served as an AARP-New York Executive Council Member since 2016, and was named Commissioner of the New York City Commission on Human Rights in 2019.
Related Archival Materials at the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
The papers of Rocky Chin's wife, May Chen, are also located at this repository. See the May Chen Papers (WAG 301).
Scope and Contents
Spanning between 1966 to 2016, with the bulk of materials from 1984-2001, this collection documents Rockwell "Rocky" Chin's work as an activist, his involvement in political campaigns, and his teaching. Consisting of both paper and electronic formats, Rocky Chin's collection contains correspondence, memoranda, meeting minutes, newsletters, publications and reports, legal briefs, brochures, event and conference programs, speech and article drafts, flyers, press releases, and newspaper clippings. A large portion of the collection pertains to Chin's service on the New York City Commission on Human Rights (HRC) and materials related to Asian American movement groups like Basement Workshop, APA labor unions, the demonstrations and rallies organized around redistricting issues, and Asian American involvement in various local and national political campaigns. There are also collected publications, reports, and audiovisual recordings related to Asian American cultural events and labor activism. The publications in this collection include books and studies from national press outlets as well as issues of newsletters and periodicals from local community groups across the country and activist organizations. There is a portion of materials documenting Chin's 2001 run for City Council representative for District 1, which includes completed candidate questionnaires and surveys, printed campaign literature, printouts of digital photographs, a campaign banner, and photographic contact sheets. To a lesser extent, the collection contains Chin's teaching materials for his courses on Asian American studies. Some materials in this collection may have been created by Chin's wife, May Chen.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Separated Materials
Approximately 1.5 linear feet of books, newsletters, and comic books were separated for library cataloging.
Asian Americans -- Economic conditions.; Asian Americans -- New York (State) -- New York.; Asian Americans -- Civil rights.; New York (N.Y.) -- Politics and government.; Asian Americans -- Politics and government.; Asian Americans -- Social conditions.; Asian Americans -- Legal status, laws, etc.; Asian Americans -- Political activity; Discrimination against Asian Americans.; Asian Americans and mass media; Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance; Basement Workshop; Chin, Rocky, 1947-; Chen, May Ying; New York (N.Y.). City Commission on Human Rights; Asian American Bar Association of New York
- Series I. Activism, 1968-2016; 9.75 Linear Feet in 17 manuscript boxes, 1 flat box, and 5 oversize folders in shared housing.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  The Activism series consists of materials documenting Rocky Chin's organizing and professional work with the New York City Commission on Human Rights, as well as the cultural events, strikes, and demonstrations in which he was involved. Materials include newsletters, correspondence, memos, meeting minutes, conference programs, brochures, booklets, flyers, speeches, T-shirts, posters, demonstration signs, optical discs, and a VHS tape. Of note are the materials documenting the organization and implementation of the first New York City Hall conference roundtable in 1992 addressing the concerns of the city's Asian Pacific American communities. These documents include press releases, memos, correspondence, reports, schedules, invitations, speeches, summaries and lists of attendees and issues.
  A large portion of the Activism series consists of research files which informs Rocky Chin's work in his various organizational roles, his work at the New York City Commission on Human Rights, his interests as a professor, and while campaigning. Some of these materials highlight various issues such as employment discrimination, Japanese American World War II incarceration and reparations, language rights, redistricting and rezoning initiatives, the Asian American studies movement, city projects (e.g. Chung Park Project, Foley Square Courthouse Project), the Vincent Chin case, negative media depictions of Asian Americans, among many other subjects. These research files include materials such as periodicals, publications, reports, legal briefs, newspaper clippings, and event and conference programs.
  - Asian American Movement, 1968-1988 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - Health Care in Chinatown, 1968, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Chinatown Housing Committee Study, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Asians in America Bibliography, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Asian Movement – Asian News Service, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Basement Workshop, 1970-1985 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters and Promotional Material, 1970-1978, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Publications, circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Reports and Newsletters, 1970-1989 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Chinatown Street Fair, 1971-1973 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - The Philippines, 1971-1973, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Harry Wong, circa 1972 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Asian Americans for Action Newsletter, 1972-1975 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - New York Asian Coalition, 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Canada - Summer Youth Conference Program, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - United Asian Communities Center – Bulletin Activities, 1973-1976 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters and Promotional Material, 1973-1977, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Asian Americans for Equal Opportunity Newsletters, 1973-1975, 1986-1988 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Periodicals and Event Programs, 1973-1988 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Publications, 1973-1988 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Asian American Student Association Periodicals, 1974-1978, 1980-1988 (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
  - Event Ephemera, 1975-1981 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Mao Memorial Speech, 1976 September (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Asian American Student Organizations, 1976-1988, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Asian American History Television Series Proposal, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Young/Chin v. U.S.A., 1978 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - APA Heritage Festival Programs, 1979-1981 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Asian American Student Associations, 1979-1989 (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
  - T-Shirt – V. Chin (6-19-82), circa 1980s (Box 23)
  - Asian Americans and Politics, 1980-1992, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Unity, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - NCRR (National Coalition Reparations Redress), 1980-1986 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Asian American Student Association Periodicals, 1980-1988, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - C.A.N. Charlie Chan, 1980-1981 (Box 10, Folder 3-4)
  - Racism in Film, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Asians in Media, 1981, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Reports and Periodicals, 1982-1989 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - The Philippines, 1982-1990, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Publications – Japanese Americans, 1983-1997 (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
  - Racist Violence, 1983-1984 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - News Clippings – Vincent Chin, 1983-1984, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Democratic Party – Asian Caucus, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - AALC (Asian American Law Center), 1984-1985 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Chinese Women of America Calendar, 1985 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - AALC Walk-in Legal Clinic in Chinatown, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Year of the Dragon, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - LDC (Chung Park Local Development Corporation) Correspondence and Mailing List, 1985-1986 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - CPA (Chinese Progressive Association), 1995-1997 (Box 12, Folder 6-7)
  - South Africa, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Asians in New York City, 1986-1991 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Dorothy Chin Brandt, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - T-Shirt – National Rainbow Coalition's 1st Annual Biennial Convention, 1987 (Box 23)
  - CAAAV (Committee Against Anti-Asian Violence), 1987-1994 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Anti-Asian Bias Complaints, CAAAV, etc., 1987-1993 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - The Economic Status of Americans of Asian Descent: An Exploratory Investigation, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Speaking Out: Asian American Periodicals, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Asian American Bar Association (National and Local Correspondence), 1988-1989 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Transcript of Round Table Conference on Asian Civil Rights Issues for the 1990s, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - AABANY (Asian American Bar Association of New York) - Rocky Chin, 1989-1993 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - AABANY - Minutes of Committee Meetings, 1989-1990 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Periodicals – Typhoon, A. Magazine, and Echoes, 1990s (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - T-Shirt – UNITY, circa 1990s (Box 23)
  - Language Rights Coalition, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Mineta Statement on Language Rights, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Theater Hearings, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - New York City Districting Commission, 1990-1991 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Reports and Publications, 1990-1994, 2005 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Hiring Audit, 1990-1992 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Federal Courthouse (Foley Square), 1991 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Redistricting Proposal Booklet, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Cornell Symposium on Asian American Studies, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - AABANY Asian Crime Victims Project, 1991-1993, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Foley Square, 1991-1992 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Asian American Roundtable Logistics, 1991-1992 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Roundtable Responses, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Lunar New Year Event Program, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Asian Roundtable: City Agencies/Guidelines, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Political Empowerment, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Roundtable Lists, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Packet from July 20, 1992 Inter-Agency Meeting, 1992 July 20 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - March on D.C. Save Our Cities, Save Our Children, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - APALA (Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance) Founding Convention, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Publications, 1992, 1996 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Columbia Human Rights Law Review, 1993 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - AABANY Foundation, 1993-1997 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - NAPABA (National Asian Pacific Bar Association), 1993-1995 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - NAPABA Civil Rights Committee, 1994-1999 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition Catalog – DMZ XING, 1994 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Labor, 1994 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - NAPALC (National Asian Pacific American Legal Consortium) - Audit of Anti Asian Violence, 1994-1998 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Delegate Materials, 1996 Democratic National Convention (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Publications and Reports, 1996-1998 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Asian Crime Victims Project, 1996-1998 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Audiovisual Material – Reminiscences: A Collection of Movies by Tom Tam, 1969-1978, 1997 (Box Shared Tamiment 056)
  - Exhibition Ephemera, 1997-2003 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - ECASU (East Coast Asian Student Union Conference), 1997 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - National Review Magazine Cover Controversy, 1997 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - National Review Magazine Cover Controversy, 1997 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - ECASU Conferences, 1997-1998 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - ECASU Program Committee, 1997-1998 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - NAPABA Civil Rights Committee Resource Handbook, 1998 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - NAPALSA (National Asian Pacific American Law Student Association) Annual Conference Program, 1998 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - NAPABA and AABANY Event Programs, 1998-2002 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Asian Pacific Islander American Caucus, 2000 Democratic Race, 1999-2000 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Asian Pacific American Access to Justice Summit, 1999 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Delta Reunion Memory Book, 1999 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - T-Shirt – Coalition of Asian Pacific Americans, Asian Pacific American Heritage Festival, 2000-2009 (Box 23)
  - T-Shirt – Immigrant Workers Freedom Ride, circa 2000s (Box 23)
  - T-Shirt – APALA 10th Biennial Convention, circa 2000s (Box 23)
  - T-Shirt – APALA, Making Waves, circa 2000s (Box 23)
  - T-Shirt – Asian American Arts Alliance, circa 2000s (Box 23)
  - Banner – "We the People Say No to the Bush Agenda", circa 2000s (Box 23)
  - Asian/Pacific American Heritage Month, 2000 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Publications and Reports, 2000-2004 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Asian American Studies Events, 2003 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Immigrant Workers Freedom Ride, 2003 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - T-Shirt – Immigrant Workers Freedom Ride, 2003 (Box 23)
  - Chinese Historical Society of American Publications, 2003-2006 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Newspapers – Sing Tao Daily and the China Press, 2003 (Box Shared Tamiment 054, Folder 9)
  - Museum of Chinese in America Program, circa 2004 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - David Wong, 2004 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - New York State Board of Elections vs. Lopez Torres, 2004-2007; cuid36460 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_WAG_325_ER_1)
  - Publications, 2004-2006 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Labor and Voting, 2004-2007 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Signs – APALA and Local 23-25, circa 2005 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Democratic Mayoral Candidates Debate and CCBA (Chinese Consolidated Benevolent Association), 2005 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - City Council District Profiles, circa 2006, 2011 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Museum of Chinese in America, 2006-2007 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - T-Shirt – Soundfest: Asian Americans in Music, 2007 (Box 23)
  - New York Immigration Coalition Fundraising Committee Meeting, September 20, 2007, 2007-2008 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - The New York Immigration Coalition Board of Directors, 2007-2008 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Reports and Publications, 2007-2012 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Korean Peninsula Peace Forum, 2008 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Audiovisual Material – 7th AAARI Annual Banquet, 2008-10-30; cuid36461 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_WAG_325_ER_2)
  - Campaign Poster – Daniel Squadron for New York State Senate, 2008 (Box Shared Tamiment 152, Folder 1)
  - YKASEC (Young Korean American Service and Education Center) 24th Anniversary Gala Program, 2008 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Asian American/Asian Research Institute Publications, 2008-2013 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Obama '08, 2008 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Campaign Signs – Asian Americans Pacific Islanders for Obama, 2008 (Box Shared Tamiment 054, Folder 10)
  - T-Shirt - APALA 10th Biennial Convention, 2009 (Box 23)
  - Campaign Poster – S.J. Jung for City Council, 2009 (Box Shared Tamiment 057, Folder 8)
  - Sign – Triangle Shirtwaist Factory Fire Memorial, 2011 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Reports and Publications, 2011-2016 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Sign – Fandang Obon, circa 2013-2016 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Publications and Reports, 2013-2014 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Publications and Reports, 2015-2016 (Box 21, Folder 3)
- Series II. Political Campaigns, 1985-1992, 1999-2001; 1.75 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes.
  The Political Campaigns series documents Rocky Chin's involvement in various New York City elections, including Jesse Jackson's presidential campaign in 1988, David Dinkin's mayoral campaign in 1989, and Sau Ngar Li and Danny Yip's 1999 run for the District 2 Community School Board Elections. Materials include correspondence, memos, press releases, newspaper clippings, statements, flyers, event programs, invitations, mailers, brochures, speeches, schedules, and meeting notes. In addition to these types of materials, Chin's own run for city council representative is also documented by completed candidate questionnaires and surveys, printed campaign literature, printouts of digital photographs, a campaign banner, and photographic contact sheets. Rocky Chin was a delegate at the 1996 and 2000 Democratic National Conventions, and supported Barack Obama's presidential candidacy in 2008, but the materials he collected from these roles are included in the Activism series, since it does not appear that he had a larger role in the campaigns.
  - Asian Americans for David Dinkins, 1985-1992 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Kee/Friedlander Race, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Asian Americans for Jesse Jackson '88, 1987-1991 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - Campaign Pennants – New Yorkers for Jesse Jackson '88, 1988 (Box Shared Tamiment 054, Folder 11)
  - School Board Elections News Clippings, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - District 2 School Board Elections, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Button – Vote Danny Yip and Sau Ngar Li, 1999 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Chinese Press on City Council Election, 1999-2001 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Press Releases and Contacts, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Printed Campaign Literature for City Council Run, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Photographs and Contact Sheets, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Press Contacts and Clippings, 2000-2001 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - City Council Race Press Clips, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Grand Street Station, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Completed Candidate Questionnaires, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - Campaign Banner – Rocky for City Council, 2000-2001 (Box 24)
- Series III. Teaching, 1973, 1980-1989, 1995; 0.25 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box.
  The materials in this series were expressly collected to develop course content at Hunter Colleges and the City College of New York, and include legal briefs, articles and readings, and newspaper clippings. This series also contains correspondence, syllabi, flyers, teaching observations, course flyers, and blank exams. Many of the research files he collected in his activism work informs the Asian American studies courses he taught, such as "Asian American Experience: Contemporary Issues," "US Policy Towards Asia - Asian Americans," and "Asian Americans Civil Rights and the Law."
  - Asian Americans and Law, 1973, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)